Pedro E. Harunari

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER · STATISTICAL PHYSICS

Department of Physics and Materials Science, University of Luxembourg, Campus Limpertsberg, 162a avenue de la Faïencerie, L-1511 Luxembourg (G. D. Luxembourg)

Personal Profile

Currently, I hold a postdoctoral researcher position at the University of Luxembourg, working under the supervision of Prof. Massimiliano Esposito. My Ph.D. in physics was obtained from the University of São Paulo, Brazil, where I engaged in extensive research and teaching activities. As an active researcher in statistical physics, my focus is on understanding and taming fluctuations of systems outside thermal equilibrium, alongside their thermodynamic properties. I am particularly interested in extending the description of stochastic thermodynamics in the presence of hidden degrees of freedom by pinpointing the relevant quantities, deriving practical expressions for real-world challenges, and connecting to the study of phase transitions, biophysics, chemical reaction networks, complex systems, and more.

Education

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Postdoctoral researcher

Dec 2022 - Current

- Member of the group Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics
- Supervised by Prof. Massimiliano Esposito

University of São Paulo

São Paulo, Brazil

Doctorate in Physics Mar 2018 - Nov 2022

- Thesis: "The role of time in nonequilibrium: transition-based coarse-graining, phase transitions and heat engines" DOI:10.11606/T.43.2022.tde-14122022-084103
- · Advisor: Prof. Dr. Carlos E. Fiore
- · Allowed to join the program without a Master's degree
- Approved with the highest grades in every course
- Teaching assistant experience during three semesters, both in graduate and undergraduate levels

University of São Paulo São Paulo

Bachelor in Physics

Feb 2014 - Nov 2017

- 1.5 years of research training activities
- One semester as teaching assistant
- · Complementary courses at: IMPA, CBPF and ICTP-SAIFR

List of Publications _____

11 articles published in internationally renowned journals and 4 preprints.

From Google Scholar: 216 citations, h-index 8.

•	• PE Harunari, CE Fiore, AC Barato, "Interence of entropy production for periodically driven systems"
	arXiv:2406.12792 (preprint)
	DELLa mani C. Dal Carrie VII annota M. Dalattini "Materallia mita afranca militari manatana da manata"

 PE Harunari, S Dal Cengio, V Lecomte, M Polettini, "Mutual linearity of nonequilibrium network currents" arXiv:2402.13193 (accepted in Physical Review Letters)

2024

2024

 PE Harunari, "Unveiling nonequilibrium from multifilar events" arXiv:2402.00837 (preprint)

2024

 A Garilli, PE Harunari, M Polettini, "Fluctuation relations for a few observable currents at their own beat" arXiv:2312.07505 (preprint)

2023

• F Avanzini, M Bilancioni, V Cavina, S Dal Cengio, M Esposito, G Falasco, D Forastiere, N Freitas, A Garilli, PE Harunari, V Lecomte, A Lazarescu, SGM Srinivas, C Moslonka, I Neri, E Penocchio, WD Piñeros, M Polettini, A Raghu, P Raux, K Sekimoto, A Soret, "Methods and Conversations in (Post)Modern Thermodynamics" SciPost Phys. Lect. Notes 80

2024

• F Hawthorne, PE Harunari, MJ de Oliveira, CE Fiore, "Nonequilibrium thermodynamics of the majority vote model"

Entropy **25** (8), 1230

PE Harunari, A Garilli, and M Polettini, "The beat of a current"
 Physical Review E 107 (4), L042105

2022

• PE Harunari, A Dutta, M Polettini, and É Roldán, "What to learn from a few visible transitions' statistics?"

JUNE 24, 2024

	Physical Review X 12, 041026	2022
•	IN Mamede, PE Harunari, BAN Akasaki, K Proesmans, and CE Fiore, "Obtaining efficient thermal engines from	
	interacting Brownian particles under time-periodic drivings"	
	Physical Review E 105 (2), 024106	2022
•	CE Fiore, PE Harunari, CEF Noa, and GT Landi, "Current fluctuations in nonequilibrium discontinuous phase transitions"	
	Physical Review E 104 (6), 064123	2021
•	PE Harunari, S Fernando Filho, CE Fiore, and A Rosas, "Maximal power for heat engines: Role of asymmetric interaction times"	
	Physical Review Research 3 (2), 023194	2021
•	PE Harunari, CE Fiore, and K Proesmans, "Exact statistics and thermodynamic uncertainty relations for a periodically driven electron pump"	
	Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 53 (37), 374001	2020
•	CEF Noa, PE Harunari, MJ de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Entropy production as a tool for characterizing nonequilibrium phase transitions"	
	Physical Review E 100 (1), 012104	2019
•	JM Encinas, PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Fundamental ingredients for discontinuous phase transitions in the inertial majority vote model"	
	Scientific reports 8 (1), 1-9	2018
•	PE Harunari, MM de Oliveira, and CE Fiore, "Partial inertia induces additional phase transition in the majority vote model"	
	Physical Review E 96 (4), 042305	2017

Work Experience

(Post) Modern Thermodynamics - School and workshop

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Organizer

Dec 2022

- Approximately, 100 participants from abroad and 30 from Luxembourg
- Conference consisting of 10 school lectures, 8 workshop sessions, and one poster session.
- Shared teaching duties of the lecture "Continuous-time Markov chain: basics, first-passages and thermodynamics" with Ken Sekimoto.
- Editorial duties on the preparation of lecture notes "Methods and Conversations in (Post) Modern Thermodynamics".
- Co-organizers: Matteo Polettini, Vasco Cavina, William Piñeros.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy

Visiting researcher

May 2022 – Jun 2022

· Visitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

University of Luxembourg

Luxembourg, Luxembourg

Visiting researcher

Apr 2021 – Feb 2022

- Visitor at Massimiliano Esposito's Complex Systems and Statistical Mechanics group.
- Supervised by Matteo Polettini.

University of Aalto

Helsinki, Finland

Visiting researcher

Dec 2021 – Jan 2022

• Visitor at Jukka Pekola's PICO group.

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

Trieste, Italy
Jul 2021 - Sep 2021

Visiting researcherVisitor at Édgar Roldán's group.

Statistical Physics seminar series

online

2018 - 2020

Organizer 2020

• 21 seminars virtually presented during the COVID lockdown, mostly by professors, for a broad audience of students and researchers across Brazil and other countries. Co-organizer: Carlos E. Fiore.

University of São Paulo São Paulo

Teaching assistant

- Thermodynamics (2020);
- Statistical Mechanics (2018 and 2019);
- Graduate level Statistical Mechanics (2018).

JUNE 24, 2024 2

University of São Paulo São Paulo

Undergraduate researcher 2015 - 2017

- · Research training program.
- Supervisors: Mário J. de Oliveira (2015-2016), and Carlos E. Fiore (2016-2017).

Skills.

Programming Python, Mathematica, C.

Miscellaneous Usage of clusters, LTEX, Ubuntu Linux, teaching.

Prizes and Grants

2023 Honorable mention for distinguished Ph.D. thesis in Exact and Earth Sciences, University of São Pau
--

- 2023 Best Ph.D. thesis in Statistical and Computational Physics (national level), Brazilian Physical Society
- 2022 **Best Ph.D. thesis prize**, Institute of Physics University of São Paulo
- 2022 Honorable mention for distinguished publication, Institute of Physics University of São Paulo
- 2021 **Intership grant**, grant for 11 months of internship abroad (BEPE FAPESP)
- 2018 **Ph.D. fellowship**, FAPESP 4 years grant for the Doctorate without Masters degree program
- 2017 Undergrad research fellowship, FAPESP grant for the Undergraduate research program
- 2016 Undergrad research fellowship, CNPq grant for the Undergraduate research program

Events attended

Dissipative Processes in Molecular Systems

Padova, Italy

University of Padova

2024

• Poster: "Inferring dissipation by monitoring reservoirs"

Journées de Physique Statistique, 42nd edition

Paris, France

École Normale Supérieure de Paris

202

• Talk: "Unveiling nonequilibrium from multifilar events"

XXVII Sitges Conference on Statistical Mechanics

Sitges, Spain

Universitat de Barcelona

2023

• Talk: "Thermodynamics at the beat of transitions"

Workshop on Stochastic Thermodynamics - WOST IV

online

The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)

2023

• Talk: "Fluctuation relation at the beat of a current"

Physics of Life: Students and Postdocs Edition

New York, United States of America

The Center for the Physics of Biological Function, CUNY/Princeton

2023

• Talk: "Thermodynamics through the lens of transitions"

Fluctuations and First Passage Problems

Stockholm, Sweden

• Talk: "Thermodynamics at the beat of transitions"

Journées de Physique Statistique, 42nd edition

Paris, France

École Normale Supérieure de Paris

• <u>Talk</u>: "Transition-based coarse-graining"

The 47th Conference of the Middle European Cooperation in Statistical Physics

Erice, Italy

MECO 47

NORDITA

• Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"

São Paulo, Brazil

Brazilian Physical Society

Autumn meeting

2022

• Poster: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"

online

National Statistical Physics Meeting

online

Universidade Federal de São João del-Rei (UFSJ)

2021

• Talk: "Inferences from Statistics of a Few Observable Transitions"

JUNE 24, 2024 3

Statistical Physics of Complex Systems	Trieste, Italy
The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics (ICTP)	2021
Poster: "Entropy production fluctuation in phase transitions"	
Bangalore School on Statistical Physics XII	online
International Center for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS)	2021
Autumn meeting	online
Brazilian Physical Society	2021
• <u>Talk</u> : "Entropy Production fluctuations in nonequilibrium transitions"	
Workshop on Stochastic Thermodynamics - WOST II	online
Santa Fe Institute	2021
APS March Meeting	online
American Physical Society	2021
• <u>Talk</u> : "Quantitative compartison of different time-periodic Thermodynamic Uncerainty Relations"	
Quantum Thermodynamics of Non-equilibrium systems	online
Donostia International Physics Center	2020
Statistical Physics Seminar Series	online
University of São PauloTalk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: Schnakenberg, FT and TUR"	2020
	aulina
Autumn meeting Brazilian Physical Society	online 2020
Talk: "Stochastic pump as a model to study nonequilibrium properties"	2020
Quantum Thermodynamics for Young Scientists	Bad Honnef, Germany
Wilhelm and Else Heraeus-Foundation	2020
• <u>Poster</u> : "Time assymetric reciprocity relations for an arbitrarily long single-particle stochastic pum	np and its exact solution"
"Coloquinho"	São Paulo, Brazil
series of talks organized by IFT-UNESP, ICTP-SAIFR students	2019
• Invited talk: "Stochastic Thermodynamics: basics and some modern aspects"	
Physics Giants: Einstein Week	São Paulo, Brazil
series of talks organized by USP students	2019
• <u>Invited talk</u> : "Einstein's contributions to Statistical Mechanics"	
Languages	
English Full professional proficiency	
Portuguese Native proficiency	
Spanish Limited working proficiency	

Peer-review contributions

PRL, PRX, PRX Quantum, PRE, PRA, JPhysA, JPhyComm

June 24, 2024